<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  Susceptible and protective HLA class 1 alleles against dengue fever and dengue hemorrhagic fever patients in a Malaysian population.
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">
   The human leukocyte antigen alleles have been implicated as probable genetic markers in predicting the susceptibility and/or protection to severe manifestations of dengue virus (DENV) infection. In this present study, we aimed to investigate for the first time, the genotype variants of HLA Class 1(-A and -B) of DENV infected patients against healthy individuals in Malaysia.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="METHODOLOGY/PRINCIPAL FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">
   This study was carried out with 92 dengue disease patients and 95 healthy controls from three different ethnic groups (Malay, Chinese and Indian) in Malaysia. All patients with clinical and laboratory confirmation of DENV infection were typed for the HLA-A and B loci, using polymerase chain reaction-sequence specific primer techniques. In our total population, a significant increase for HLA-B*53 (P = 0.042, Pc = 1.008) allele and a significant decrease for A*03 (P = 0.015, Pc = 0.18, OR = 5.23, 95% CI = 1.19-23.02) and B*18 (P = 0.017, Pc = 0.408) alleles were noted in DHF patients as compared to healthy donors. We also observed that in the Malay DHF patients, allele B*13 (P = 0.049, Pc = 1.176, OR = 0.18, 95% CI = 0.03-0.90) was present at a significantly higher frequency in this population while allele HLA-B*18 (P = 0.024, Pc = 0.576) was seen to be negatively associated with DHF.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS/SIGNIFICANCE" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">
   These are the first findings on genetic polymorphisms in our population and we conclude that: (1) In our total population, HLA-B*53 probably involve in disease susceptibility, while the HLA-A*03 and HLA-B*18 may confer protection from progression to severe disease; (2) In the Malay population, HLA-B*13 and B*18 are probably associated in disease susceptibility and protection, respectively. These results could furnish as a valuable predictive tool to identify ethnically different individuals at risk and/or protection from severe forms of DENV infection and would provide valuable informations for the design of future dengue vaccine.
  </AbstractText>
 </abstract>
</article>