<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  Flow cytometry analysis with a new FITC-conjugated monoclonal antibody-3E12 for HLA-B*57:01 rapid screening in prevention of abacavir hypersensitivity in HIV-1-infected patients.
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">
   Rapid screening for the detection of HLA-B*57:01 in the prevention of abacavir hypersensitivity in HIV-1-infected patients is a hallmark for clinical services.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">
   The aim of this work was to analyze the utility of flow cytometry with a new FITC-conjugated B-17 monoclonal antibody (mAb3E12) for HLA-B*57:01 screening in a Spanish cohort of 577 HIV-1+ individuals.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">
   Cryopreserved peripheral blood mononuclear cell samples from HIV-1+ individuals were analyzed by flow cytometry with the mAb 3E12 that recognizes both HLA-B*57 and HLA-B*58 alleles (members of the group specificity, HLA-B17). Patients DNA samples had been previously typed for HLA-B*57:01 with PCR-SSO or PCR-SSP and additional DNA sequencing (EPI Study). The results obtained by flow cytometry were compared with the results obtained by the DNA-PCR techniques.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">
   By flow cytometry, 46 samples (7.97%) were positive for HLA-B17, 530 (91.86%) were negative, and 1 (0.17%) was undetermined. All samples found negative by flow cytometry were negative for HLA-B*57:01 by DNA-PCR. Of the HLA-B17 positive samples, 31 (67.4%) were positive for HLA-B*57:01, 2 (3.25%) were positive for HLA-B*57:03, 11 (26.1%) were positive for HLA-B*58, and 2 (3.25%) were negative for both HLA-B*57 and HLA-B*58 antigens. The undetermined sample was negative for HLA-B*57 and HLA-B*58 alleles by DNA-PCR.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">
   This study shows that flow cytometry with mAb3E12 is a highly sensitive method (no false negatives) to implement prior to DNA-PCR analysis for rapid screening of HLA-B*57:01. Additional confirmation by molecular HLA typing method would be required in less than 10% of the cohort of HIV-1-infected individuals.
  </AbstractText>
 </abstract>
</article>