<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  Human leukocyte antigen B distribution in HIV discordant cohort from India.
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <AbstractText>
   Limited reports are available on association of HLA-B with HIV infection from India, a home to the third largest population of HIV infected people in the world. This emphasizes the need to have more information specifically the genetic constitution of HIV serodiscordant couples (DCs), where one spouse is seropositive (HSP) while the other remains seronegative (HSN) even after repeated exposure. Hence, aim of this study was to document association of HLA-B with HIV infection in DCs living in Mumbai, India. A cohort was designed to enroll DCs attending the ICTC/Shakti Clinic of KEM Hospital, Mumbai. A group of unexposed volunteers were also enrolled as healthy controls (HC). HLA-B alleles were typed using sequence-specific oligonucleotide probes. Allele frequency comparison was done using 2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xc3\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x972 contingency tables. Results were considered significant, when p&lt;0.05 with two-tailed Fishers exact test. At HLA-B locus, the frequencies of HLA-B*40;-B*35;-B*07;-B*15;-B*51;-B*44;-B*52;-B*37 and -B*57 were found in decreasing order in the population. Frequency of HLA-B*35 allele was significantly higher (HSP vs HSN; p&lt;0.02 and HSP vs HC; p&lt;0.04) in HSP. HLA-B*40 (HSN vs HSP; p&lt;0.01 and HC vs HSP; p&lt;0.01) and HLA-B*18 (HSN vs HSP; p&lt;0.02) were significantly associated with HSN. Both HSN and HC had similar HLA-B*35 and -B*40 allele frequency. HLA-B*57 allele was observed in 15 individuals (3.69%). However, HLA-B*57:01 which is known to be associated with adverse reactions against Abacavir was observed in 7 of them. HLA-B*39 was observed exclusively in HSP. Our observation in DCs confirmed the association of HLA-B*35 with susceptibility while HLA-B*40 (specifically *B40:06), -B*18 with protection. These identified alleles can be used as possible marker associated with HIV transmission. In India, HLA screening is not carried out before initiation of HIV treatment. However, the presence of HLA-B*57:01 in the population emphasizes the importance of such screening to predict/avoid Abacavir hypersensitivity.
  </AbstractText>
 </abstract>
</article>