<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  Lower Viral Loads and Slower CD4+ T-Cell Count Decline in MRKAd5 HIV-1 Vaccinees Expressing Disease-Susceptible HLA-B*58:02.
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">
   HLA strongly influences human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) disease progression. A major contributory mechanism is via the particular HLA-presented HIV-1 epitopes that are recognized by CD8(+) T-cells. Different populations vary considerably in the HLA alleles expressed. We investigated the HLA-specific impact of the MRKAd5 HIV-1 Gag/Pol/Nef vaccine in a subset of the infected Phambili cohort in whom the disease-susceptible HLA-B*58:02 is highly prevalent.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="METHODS">
   Viral loads, CD4(+) T-cell counts, and enzyme-linked immunospot assay-determined anti-HIV-1 CD8(+) T-cell responses for a subset of infected antiretroviral-naive Phambili participants, selected according to sample availability, were analyzed.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="RESULTS">
   Among those expressing disease-susceptible HLA-B*58:02, vaccinees had a lower chronic viral set point than placebo recipients (median, 7240 vs 122 500 copies/mL; P = .01), a 0.76 log10 lower longitudinal viremia level (P = .01), and slower progression to a CD4(+) T-cell count of &lt;350 cells/mm(3) (P = .02). These differences were accompanied by a higher Gag-specific breadth (4.5 vs 1 responses; P = .04) and magnitude (2300 vs 70 spot-forming cells/10(6) peripheral blood mononuclear cells; P = .06) in vaccinees versus placebo recipients.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS">
   In addition to the known enhancement of HIV-1 acquisition resulting from the MRKAd5 HIV-1 vaccine, these findings in a nonrandomized subset of enrollees show an HLA-specific vaccine effect on the time to CD4(+) T-cell count decline and viremia level after infection and the potential for vaccines to differentially alter disease outcome according to population HLA composition.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="CLINICAL TRIALS REGISTRATION">
   NCT00413725, DOH-27-0207-1539.
  </AbstractText>
 </abstract>
</article>