<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  Identification of the impact on T- and B- cell epitopes of human papillomavirus type-16 E6 and E7 variant in Southwest China.
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <AbstractText>
   Cervical cancers almost are infected by human papillmavirus (HPV), encoding E6 and E7 oncoproteins which are regard as ideal targets on the mechanism of this disease and development of vaccines. HLA (human leukocyte antigen) participates in the local immune response to prevent tumor invasion and progression. But due to highly polymorphism of HLA, prediction shows its importance in this study. More effective immunoinformatics was used for predicting epitopes from HPV-16 E6 and E7, including T- and B-cell epitopes. Eight substitutions are detected. Specifically speaking, for HLA-I, HLA-A*33:03 (26), HLA-B*13:01 (14), HLA-C*03:02 (5) for E6 and HLA-A*02:01 (6), HLA-B*40:01 (5), HLA-C*03:04 (4) for E7 are most frequency. Epitope
   <sub>
    41-48
   </sub>
   EVYDFAFR for HLA-A*33:03 (0.1) for E6 has best binding affinity, as well as HLA*02:01 and HLA-B*40:01 (0.2) for E7. The mutations of D25E and L83V of E6 and N29S of E7 produce new epitopes, and the percentile values change with them. For HLA-II, seventeen epitopes in the reference at percentile value from 0.22 to 4.76, while in variant from 0.22 to 4.96. For the B-cell epitopes, three most potent epitopes for E6 were listed, and N29S lead the growth of score from 0.81 to 0.83. In summary, E6
   <sub>
    40-55
   </sub>
   REVYDFAFRDLCIVYR and E7
   <sub>
    11-22
   </sub>
   YMLDLQPETTDL are the important regions, containing the majority of predicted epitopes. E6 72-83 for HLA-A*02:01 and E6 74-84 for HLA-B*15:02 maybe are the new direct for therapeutic vaccine aimed at L83V variants. HLA-DRB1*15:02 is better binder with T cell in our HLA class II. It is a systematic, detail recognition for T- and B-cell epitopes of HPV-16 E6 and E7 from Southwest China, which may be helpful to design vaccines specifically for women in Southwest China and testing methods specifically for this region. The results of our study may contribute to future researches on vaccines improvement, or screening methods for a particular population.
  </AbstractText>
 </abstract>
</article>