<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  HLA-B*14 allele predicts HIV-1 mother-to-child-transmission, in Salvador, Brazil.
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">
   Class I human leukocyte antigens, especially the molecules encoded at the B locus (HLA-B), are associated with AIDS progression risk. Different groups of HLA-B alleles have been associated to a protective effect or increasing susceptibility to HIV infection and are expressed from the earliest stages of gestation.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">
   The aim of this study was to evaluate which variants of HLA-B are associated with the risk of HIV vertical transmission in infected pregnant women and in their offspring, in a referral center in Salvador Bahia.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">
   We performed HLA-B genotyping in 52 HIV-infected mothers and their children exposed to HIV-1 during pregnancy (N=65) in Salvador, Brazil. We compared the HLA-B alleles frequency in mothers, uninfected and infected children, according to the use of antiretroviral prophylaxis.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">
   Absence of antiretroviral antenatal and postnatal prophylaxis was significantly associated with vertical transmission of HIV-1 (p=&lt;0.01, and p=&lt;0.01 respectively). Frequency of HLA-B*14 (29.2%, p=0.002), HLA-B*18 (16.7%, p=0.04) or HLA-B*14:1 (20.8%, p=0.01) alleles subgroups were significantly higher in HIV-1 infected children and persisted (HLA-B*14, p=0.04) even after adjusting for use of antiretroviral prophylaxis. No significant difference in expression of HLA-B alleles was observed among mothers who transmitted the virus compared to those who did not.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">
   Expression of HLA-B*14 allele in children exposed to HIV-1 is predictive of vertical transmission and reinforces the important role of genetics in mother-to-child transmission.
  </AbstractText>
 </abstract>
</article>