<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  Polyfunctional CD8+ T-Cell Response to Autologous Peptides from Protease and Reverse Transcriptase of HIV-1 Clade B.
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">
   The diversity of the HIV proteome influences the cellular response and development of an effective vaccine, particularly due to the generation of viral variants with mutations located within CD8+ T-cell epitopes. These mutations can affect the recognition of the epitopes, that may result in the selection of HIV variants with mutated epitopes (autologous epitopes) and different CD8+ T-cell functional profiles.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE">
   To determine the phenotype and functionality of CD8+ T-cell from HIV-infected Colombian patients in response to autologous and consensus peptides derived from HIV-1 clade B protease and reverse transcriptase (RT).
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="METHODS">
   By flow cytometry, we compared the ex vivo CD8+ T-cell responses from HIV-infected patients to autologous and consensus peptides derived from HIV-1 clade B protease and RT, restricted by HLA-B*35, HLA-B*44 and HLA-B*51 alleles.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="RESULTS">
   Although autologous peptides restricted by HLA-B*35 and HLA-B*44 did not show any differences compared with consensus peptides, we observed the induction of a higher polyfunctional profile of CD8+ T-cells by autologous peptides restricted by HLA-B*51, particularly by the production of interferon-\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xce\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xb3 and macrophage inflammatory protein-1\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xce\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xb2. The response by different memory CD8+ T-cell populations was comparable between autologous vs. consensus peptides. In addition, the magnitude of the polyfunctional response induced by the HLA-B*51-restricted QRPLVTIRI autologous epitope correlated with low viremia.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION">
   Autologous peptides should be considered for the evaluation of HIV-specific CD8+ Tcell responses and to reveal some relevant epitopes that could be useful for therapeutic strategies aiming to promote polyfunctional CD8+ T-cell responses in a specific population of HIV-infected patients.
  </AbstractText>
 </abstract>
</article>