<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  Association of HLA-A, -B, DRB, and DQB Alleles with Persistent HPV-16 Infection in Women from Tamil Nadu, India.
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <AbstractText>
   Women with persistent human papillomavirus (HPV) infections have a high risk of developing cervical cancer (CaCx). HPV-16 alone accounts for more than 60% of CaCx worldwide. Most of the HPV infections are transient and only a subset of women develop persistent HPV-16 infection. Many studies have shown associations of different human leukocyte antigen (HLA) alleles with HPV-mediated CaCx, but there are only a few studies globally that relate to persistent HPV-16 infection. Furthermore, such studies from India are sparse. Hence, we investigated the association of HLA-A, B, DRB, and DQB alleles with persistent HPV-16 infection and HPV-16-positive CaCx in south India (Tamil Nadu). HPV-16 persistent infection was observed in 7% of normal women. A total of 50 women with HPV-16-positive CaCx, 21 women with HPV-16 persistent infection, and 74 HPV-16-negative normal women were recruited for this study. Low-resolution typing of HLA-A, B, DRB, and DQB alleles was performed. HLA-B*44 and DRB1*07 showed a significant association with persistent HPV-16 infection (odds ratio,
   <i>
    p
   </i>
   -value\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x89=\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x8926.3, 0.03 and 4.7, 0.01, respectively). HLA-B*27 and DRB1*12 were significantly associated with both HPV-16   CaCx and persistent HPV-16 infection (23.8, 0.03; 52.9, 0.01; 9.8, 0.0009; and 13.8, 0.009; respectively). HLA-B*15 showed a negative association with HPV-16-positive CaCx (0.1, 0.01), whereas DRB1*04 exhibited protection to both HPV-16-positive CaCx and persistent HPV-16 infection (0.3, 0.0001 and 0.1, 0.0002, respectively). Thus, we show HLA allelic association with HPV-16 infection in Tamil Nadu. Larger studies on high-resolution HLA typing coupled with HPV-16 genome diversity will offer further insights into host/pathogen genome coevolution.
  </AbstractText>
 </abstract>
</article>