<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  Major Histocompatibility Complex Class I Chain-Related A and B (MICA and MICB) Gene, Allele, and Haplotype Associations With Dengue Infections in Ethnic Thais.
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">
   Major histocompatibility complex class I chain-related (MIC) A and B (MICA and MICB) are polymorphic stress molecules recognized by natural killer cells. This study was performed to analyze MIC gene profiles in hospitalized Thai children with acute dengue illness.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="METHODS">
   MIC allele profiles were determined in a discovery cohort of patients with dengue fever or dengue hemorrhagic fever (DHF) (n\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x85=\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x85166) and controls (n\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x85=\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x85149). A replication cohort of patients with dengue (n\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x85=\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x85222) was used to confirm specific MICB associations with disease.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="RESULTS">
   MICA*045 and MICB*004 associated with susceptibility to DHF in secondary dengue virus (DENV) infections (odds ratio [OR],\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x853.22; [95% confidence interval (CI), 1.18-8.84] and 1.99 [1.07-2.13], respectively), and MICB*002 with protection from DHF in secondary DENV infections (OR,\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x850.41; 95% CI, .21-.68). The protective effect of MICB*002 against secondary DHF was confirmed in the replication cohort (OR,\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x850.43; 95% CI, .22-.82) and was stronger when MICB*002 is present in individuals also carrying HLA-B*18, B*40, and B*44 alleles which form the B44 supertype of functionally related alleles (0.29, 95% CI, .14-.60).
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS">
   Given that MICB*002 is a low expresser of soluble proteins, these data indicate that surface expression of MICB*002 with B44 supertype alleles on DENV-infected cells confer a protective advantage in controlling DENV infection using natural killer cells.
  </AbstractText>
 </abstract>
</article>