<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  HLA-B*35 as a new marker for susceptibility to human T-cell lymphotropic virus type 1 (HTLV-1) Associated Myelopathy/Tropical Spastic Paraparesis (HAM/TSP) in patients living in Argentina.
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">
   Human T-cell lymphotropic virus type 1 (HTLV-1) is the etiological agent of HTLV associated myelopathy/ Tropical Spastic Paraparesis (HAM/TSP) and Adult T cell leukemia/lymphoma (ATLL), in around 2-5% of the infected individuals. Host genetic background might play a role in disease progression. Several previous studies across many countries report HLA haplotype to be one such factor. Here, we sequenced HLA-A, -B and -C of 66 individuals by Sequence-Based Typing (SBT), and compared the frequency of different alleles among ATLL patients, HAM/TSP patients, asymptomatic carriers and non-infected individuals living in Argentina.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="RESULTS">
   The frequency of HLA-A, -B and -C alleles largely matched that of the general population in Argentina. We identified HLA-A*02, HLA-B*35 and HLA-C*07 as associated to protection from ATLL (p\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x89=\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x890.031), susceptibility to HAM/TSP (p\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x89&lt;\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x890.001) and susceptibility to ATLL (p\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x89=\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x890.017), respectively. We also found a strong correlation between high proviral load (PVL) and disease (p\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x89=\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\xe2\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x80\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\\x890.008), but were unable to identify any particular allele associated with high or low PVL.
  </AbstractText>
  <AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS">
   We have found HLA-A*02, HLA-B*35 and HLA-C*07 to be associated to protection from ATLL (HLA-A*02) and susceptibility to HAM/TSP (HLA-B*35) or to ATLL (HLA-C*07), respectively. Whereas HLA-A*02 protection from ATLL has already been extensively described in other regions of the world, this is the first report that links HLA-B*35 and an increased susceptibility to HAM/TSP. As for HLA-C*07 it has previously been associated to susceptibility to HAM/TSP in other countries but in our population it has been linked to ATLL.
  </AbstractText>
 </abstract>
</article>