<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  None
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <p>
   In studies of acute hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection, the early host immune response is one of the determinants of viral persistence. The class I human leukocyte antigens (HLA), which present foreign antigen to cytolytic T cells, are integral components of this response. We hypothesized that the highly polymorphic
   <italic>
    HLA
   </italic>
   genes affect the outcome of an HCV infection. To test this hypothesis, we molecularly typed 231 persons with well-documented clearance of an HCV infection and 444 matched persistently infected persons.
   <italic>
    HLA-A*1101
   </italic>
   (odds ratio [OR], 0.49; 95% confidence interval [95% CI], 0.27 to 0.89),
   <italic>
    HLA-B*57
   </italic>
   (OR, 0.62; 95% CI, 0.39 to 1.00), and
   <italic>
    HLA-Cw*0102
   </italic>
   (OR, 0.43; 95% CI, 0.21 to 0.89) were associated with viral clearance, whereas
   <italic>
    HLA-A*2301
   </italic>
   (OR, 1.78; 95% CI, 1.01 to 3.11) and
   <italic>
    HLA-Cw*04
   </italic>
   (OR, 1.78; 95% CI, 1.21 to 2.59) were associated with viral persistence.
   <italic>
    HLA-Cw*04
   </italic>
   is in strong linkage disequilibrium with
   <italic>
    HLA-B*53
   </italic>
   and
   <italic>
    HLA-B*35
   </italic>
   , but only
   <italic>
    HLA-B*53
   </italic>
   (OR, 1.70; 95% CI, 0.95 to 3.06) and the
   <italic>
    Cw*04-B*53
   </italic>
   haplotype (OR, 1.76; 95% CI, 0.94 to 3.26) were weakly associated with viral persistence.
   <italic>
    HLA-B*53
   </italic>
   has similar, but not necessarily identical, binding specificity to some
   <italic>
    HLA-B*35
   </italic>
   subtypes (
   <italic>
    B*35-Px
   </italic>
   group). The association with the
   <italic>
    B*35-Px
   </italic>
   group was less strong than with
   <italic>
    HLA-B*53
   </italic>
   alone. The association of
   <italic>
    HLA-Cw*04
   </italic>
   with HCV persistence was codominant (two copies of the gene were more strongly associated with persistence than one copy). However,
   <italic>
    HLA-Cw*04
   </italic>
   was not associated with HCV RNA levels among the persistently infected individuals. Since Cw*04 is a ligand for the killer immunoglobulin-like receptors on natural killer cells, these cells may be involved in recovery from HCV infection. Further investigation is needed to understand the relationship between class I alleles and HCV clearance.
  </p>
 </abstract>
 <sentences/>
</article>