<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  From ZikV genome to vaccine:
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <p>
   Zika virus (ZikV) has emerged as a potential threat to human health worldwide. A member of the Flaviviridae, ZikV is transmitted to humans by mosquitoes. It is related to other pathogenic vector‐borne flaviviruses including dengue, West Nile and Japanese encephalitis viruses, but produces a comparatively mild disease in humans. As a result of its epidemic outbreak and the lack of potential medication, there is a need for improved vaccine/drugs. Computational techniques will provide further information about this virus. Comparative analysis of ZikV genomes should lead to the identification of the core characteristics that define a virus family, as well as its unique properties, while phylogenetic analysis will show the evolutionary relationships and provide clues about the proteins ancestry. Envelope glycoprotein of ZikV was obtained from a protein database and the most immunogenic epitope for T cells and B cells involved in cell‐mediated immunity, whereas B cells are primarily responsible for humoral immunity. We mainly focused on
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">
    MHC
   </styled-content>
   class I potential peptides.
   <italic>
    <styled-content style="fixed-case">
     YRIMLSVHG
    </styled-content>
   </italic>
   ,
   <italic>
    <styled-content style="fixed-case">
     VLIFLSTAV
    </styled-content>
   </italic>
   and
   <italic>
    <styled-content style="fixed-case">
     MMLELDPPF
    </styled-content>
   </italic>
   ,
   <italic>
    <styled-content style="fixed-case">
     GLDFSDLYY
    </styled-content>
   </italic>
   are the most potent peptides predicted as epitopes for
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">
    CD
   </styled-content>
   4   and
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">
    CD
   </styled-content>
   8   T cells, respectively, whereas
   <italic>
    <styled-content style="fixed-case">
     MMLELDPPF
    </styled-content>
   </italic>
   and
   <italic>
    <styled-content style="fixed-case">
     GLDFSDLYY
    </styled-content>
   </italic>
   had the highest
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">
    pMHC
   </styled-content>
   ‐I immunogenicity score and these are further tested for interaction against the
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">
    HLA
   </styled-content>
   molecules, using
   <italic>
    in silico
   </italic>
   docking techniques to verify the binding cleft epitope. However, this is an introductory approach to design an epitope‐based peptide vaccine against ZikV; we hope that this model will be helpful in designing and predicting novel vaccine candidates.
  </p>
 </abstract>
 <sentences/>
</article>