<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  HLA Class I Downregulation by HIV-1 Variants from Subtype C Transmission Pairs
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <p>
   HIV-1 downregulates human leukocyte antigen A (HLA-A) and HLA-B from the surface of infected cells primarily to evade CD8 T cell recognition. HLA-C was thought to remain on the cell surface and bind inhibitory killer immunoglobulin-like receptors, preventing natural killer (NK) cell-mediated suppression. However, a recent study found HIV-1 primary viruses have the capacity to downregulate HLA-C. The goal of this study was to assess the heterogeneity of HLA-A, HLA-B, and HLA-C downregulation among full-length primary viruses from six chronically infected and six newly infected individuals from transmission pairs and to determine whether transmitted/founder variants exhibit common HLA class I downregulation characteristics. We measured HLA-A, HLA-B, HLA-C, and total HLA class I downregulation by flow cytometry of primary CD4 T cells infected with 40 infectious molecular clones. Primary viruses mediated a range of HLA class I downregulation capacities (1.3- to 6.1-fold) which could differ significantly between transmission pairs. Downregulation of HLA-C surface expression on infected cells correlated with susceptibility to
   <italic>
    in vitro
   </italic>
   NK cell suppression of virus release. Despite this, transmitted/founder variants did not share a downregulation signature and instead were more similar to the quasispecies of matched donor partners. These data indicate that a range of viral abilities to downregulate HLA-A, HLA-B, and HLA-C exist within and between individuals that can have functional consequences on immune recognition.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>
    IMPORTANCE
   </bold>
   Subtype C HIV-1 is the predominant subtype involved in heterosexual transmission in sub-Saharan Africa. Authentic subtype C viruses that contain natural sequence variations throughout the genome often are not used in experimental systems due to technical constraints and sample availability. In this study, authentic full-length subtype C viruses, including transmitted/founder viruses, were examined for the ability to disrupt surface expression of HLA class I molecules, which are central to both adaptive and innate immune responses to viral infections. We found that the HLA class I downregulation capacity of primary viruses varied, and HLA-C downregulation capacity impacted viral suppression by natural killer cells. Transmitted viruses were not distinct in the capacity for HLA class I downregulation or natural killer cell evasion. These results enrich our understanding of the phenotypic variation existing among natural HIV-1 viruses and how that might impact the ability of the immune system to recognize infected cells in acute and chronic infection.
  </p>
 </abstract>
 <sentences/>
</article>